Margaret Goddard Holt Papers, 1814-2004 (bulk 1960-2000)
Sophia Smith Collection
Margaret Goddard Holt papers
1814-2004
1960-2000
Holt, Margaret Goddard, 1911-2004
MS 196
123 boxes (55.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Pacifist, Member, Grey Panthers, Artist. The Margaret Goddard Holt Papers primarily document the personal life and activism of Margaret Holt, but also include significant amounts of material generated by her husband, Lee E. Holt, and several generations of extended family. Her lifetime diaries are detailed and introspective, and document her life from adolescence through old age and there is extensive correspondence with family and close friends (including Jungian analyst and friend, Paula Elkisch, and painter Sarah Blakeslee Speight), fellow activists, and death row prisoners. Topics reflected in the papers include world peace and nuclear disarmament; economic, political, and social justice for disadvantaged peoples in the U.S. and abroad; the Arab-Israeli conflict; and objection to U.S. militarism and military interference by the U.S. in the affairs of other nations.
Margaret Goddard Holt was born on October 4, 1911 in Swarthmore, Pennsylvania to Fanny Whiting Reed and Harold Clarke Goddard, professor of English at Swarthmore College; she had one sister, Eleanor Goddard Worthen. She was raised a Quaker and absorbed the values of that tradition, but never joined the Society of Friends. She was also guided by Zen Buddhism, especially the teachings of Lao Tse. After graduating from Swarthmore High School in 1929, she studied art at various institutions, including the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Art Students' League in New York City, and the Cummington (Massachusetts) School of the Arts. She taught at the Shady Hill School in Cambridge, Massachusetts and at the School in Rose Valley in Rose Valley, Pennsylvania (both progressive schools), prior to her marriage in 1939 to Lee Elbert Holt (March 23, 1912 - January 23, 2004). The Holts were married for sixty-four years and had two children, Geoffrey Lincoln and Alison. In 1947, after living in Indiana, Wisconsin, New York and Connecticut, the Holts settled in Springfield, Massachusetts, where Lee taught English at American International College and Margaret worked part-time teaching art therapy to the handicapped at United Cerebral Palsy and Munson State Hospital. They moved to Amherst, Massachusetts in 1977. After the World War II bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki and the beginnings of the Cold War, Margaret Holt began her lifetime of work in peace and justice activism. She helped organize some of the major social justice demonstrations of the 1960s, including the Poor People's Campaign in Washington, D.C. in 1963; coordinated, with Lee, frequent vigils in Springfield from 1967 to 1972 in protest of the Vietnam War; co-founded the Springfield chapter of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; was a pivotal member of the Gray Panthers of the Pioneer Valley; and, beginning in 2000, corresponded weekly with death row prisoners, in addition to providing occasional financial support to their families. With Lee, Margaret Holt helped establish the Amherst (Massachusetts) Vigil for a Nuclear Free World in 1979 and from that time forward, regardless of weather, she attended weekly noon Sunday vigils on the Amherst Town Common. Margaret Holt died in Amherst, Massachusetts on January 1, 2004.
The Margaret Goddard Holt Papers consist of 55.25 linear ft. of correspondence, diaries, writings, artwork, photographs, short run and small circulation newsletters, periodicals, and publications. The collection primarily concerns Margaret Holt, and also includes significant amounts of material generated by her husband, Lee E. Holt and by several generations of extended family. The collection dates from 1814 to 2004 (bulk 1960-2000).
The papers offer a rich account of Margaret Holt's intellectual interests, political concerns, and personal affairs. Her lifetime diaries are detailed and introspective, and document her inner life, her relationships with family and friends, and her evolving world view from adolescence through old age (the diaries are closed until Jan. 1, 2028). There is extensive correspondence between Holt and her sister, Eleanor Goddard Worthen; her husband, Lee E. Holt; her close friends, including her Jungian analyst and later friend, Paula Elkisch, and the painter, Sarah Blakeslee Speight; and a wide range of more casual friends and acquaintances, fellow activists, and death row prisoners. The personal correspondence is particularly valuable in that in several instances it includes the letters of both Holt and her correspondent. Significant topics covered in letters to the editor and to politicians and elected representatives include the civil rights movement (1960s); the Vietnam War, and Watergate (1960s and 1970s); biological warfare, and the Iran-Contra scandal (1980s); the Persian Gulf War (1990s); and the Iraq War (2000s).
Materials generated by Lee E. Holt and his family, notably family correspondence and photographs, provide context to Margaret Holt's own papers and add a valuable dimension to the collection as a whole. Major topics in the papers include world peace and nuclear disarmament; economic, political, and social justice for disadvantaged peoples in the U.S. and abroad; and objection to U.S. militarism and military interference by the U.S. in the affairs of other nations. There is extensive documentation of the Arab-Israeli conflict, as Holt was sympathetic to the Palestinian position. The collection also contains a rich assortment of short run and limited circulation newsletters and printed materials generated by small, local grassroots organizations in the United States and abroad.
This collection is organized into seven series:
BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
CORRESPONDENCE
WRITINGS
ACTIVISM
ARTWORK
PHOTOGRAPHS
SUBJECT FILES
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exceptions:
Margaret Holt's diaries are closed until January 1, 2028.
Access to audiovisual materials will first require production of research copies.
Margaret Goddard Holt donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1983 to 1991. Jeanine Maland donated the remainder after Holt's death in 2005.
Amherst (Mass.) -- History -- Sources; Antinuclear movement -- United States -- History -- Sources; Arab-Israeli conflict -- 1973-1993 -- Peace; Arab-Israeli conflict -- 1993- -- Peace; Disarmament -- Peace; Artists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Capital punishment -- United States -- History -- Sources; Conscientious objectors -- United States -- History -- Sources; Death row inmates -- United States -- Correspondence; Gray Panthers -- United States -- History -- Sources; Iraq War, 2003- -- Peace; Nuclear disarmament -- History -- Sources; Older people -- United States -- Political activity; Older women -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Pacifists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Peace movements -- History -- Sources; Persian Gulf War, 1991 -- Peace; Political activists -- United States -- Biography; United States -- Military policy -- Citizen participation; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- Sources; Women with disabilities -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Women and peace -- History -- Sources; Women artists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Holt, Margaret Goddard, 1911-2004; Goddard, Harold Clarke, 1878-1950; Holt, Lee Elbert; Speight, Sarah Blakeslee, 1912-
APPENDIX: Goddard and Holt family identification (nicknames in parentheses)
Family members as a group (Creatures)
Ballou, Pauline Goddard (Pollywog, Frog): paternal aunt of Margaret Holt
Ballou, Austin (Ostrich): husband of Pauline Goddard Ballou
Goddard, Fanny Whiting Reed (Moppy, Twain): mother of Margaret Holt
Goddard, Florence Louise: (Rattlesnake, Rattle): paternal aunt of Margaret Holt
Goddard, Harold Clarke (Uncle Gawky, Poppy, Twain): father of Margaret Holt
Goddard, Mary Azooba Clarke (Zoobie): paternal grandmother of Margaret Holt
Holt, Alison: daughter of Margaret Holt
Holt, Daisy: mother of Lee E. Holt
Holt, Florence: sister of Lee E. Holt
Holt, Geoffrey Lincoln: son of Margaret Holt
Holt, Helen: sister of Lee E. Holt
Holt, Lee Cone: father of Lee E. Holt
Holt, Margaret Goddard (Smig)
Reed, Lewis: brother of Fanny Whiting Reed Goddard, m. Isabel
Uretz, Violet: cousin of Lee E. Holt
Walker, Florence Hammersly: cousin of Margaret Holt
Worthen, Eleanor Goddard (Armadillo): sister of Margaret Holt, m. Eugene Mark Worthen
Worthen, Helena Harlow (Holly): niece of Margaret Holt, daughter of Eleanor and Mark Worthen, m. Joseph Berry
Worthen, Hilary: nephew of Margaret Holt, son of Eleanor and Mark Worthen m. Kathy Weingarten
Worthen, Ben: son of Hilary Worthen and Kathy Weingarten
Worthen, Miranda: daughter of Hilary Worthen and Kathy Weingarten
Worthen, Gabrielle Zim (Gabi): daughter of Helena Harlow Worthen and Joseph Berry, m. David Kreme
Related materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the Clark-Warner Family Papers, the Frances Crowe Papers, and the Arise for Social Justice Records.
Related materials can be found in Special Collections and University Archives, W.E.B. DuBois Library, University of Massachusetts Amherst in the Amherst Disarmament Coalition Collection, the Gray Panthers of the Pioneer Valley Records, and the Gray Panthers of Hampden County.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1814-2004, 5.5 linear ft.
  This series provides a basic overview about Margaret Goddard Holt and her extended family. It is organized into four subseries: Family history, Margaret Goddard Holt, Other Family members, and Memorabilia. The series begins with genealogical and historical information, followed by biographical information about Margaret Holt, and other family members listed alphabetically by last name. Materials pertaining to Margaret Holt contain substantive writings about her, including autobiographical statements, eulogies and obituaries, and articles and clippings, as well as calendars; and records of her donations to peace, social justice, and political groups and organizations. If the amount is negligible, writings by some family members are included in this series rather than SERIES III. WRITINGS. Margaret Holt's relationships to family and friends are explained in Appendix.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1868-2003, 12 linear ft.
  This series is arranged in two subseries: Margaret Goddard Holt and Other family members. It begins with letters between Margaret Holt and her family, followed by correspondence with employers (a very small amount), friends and acquaintances, death row inmates, and letters to newspaper editors and elected government officials. Holt's correspondence contains a set of letters she designated those "which in some way help make MGH feel that her life hasn't been wasted." Correspondence within each subseries is arranged alphabetically by the author's last name. The use of nicknames is common in this series; see Appendix for identification.
- SERIES III. WRITINGS1908-2003, 8.5 linear ft.
  This series consists of three subseries, beginning with the writings of Margaret Goddard Holt and followed by Other family members, and Writings by others. In addition to essays, poems, short stories, and drafts of a book, Holt's writings also contain travel diaries of several trips to the American Southwest and to Europe. Travel diaries are complemented by correspondence written to Holt's friends during her travels, notably to Kitty and Rudy Praetz, and by Lee E. Holt's photographs in SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS. Margaret Holt's diaries overlap with her sketchbooks in SERIES V. ARTWORK, in that there are sketches in many of the former and informal diary entries in the latter. The writings of Harold Clarke Goddard and Lee E. Holt are primarily academic; those of Helen Holt consist of a booklet of privately published poems.
- SERIES IV. ACTIVISM1967-2004, 3 linear ft.
  This series, which complements SERIES VII. SUBJECTS, documents Margaret G. Holt's involvement in three distinct spheres of political activism, and is accordingly arranged in three subseries: Anthrax research protest pertains to civil actions undertaken in protest of anthrax research conducted at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst in the late 1980s and early 1990s, and includes documentation of publicity surrounding the case and of Holt's legal defense; Gray Panthers contains materials generated by Holt's work with the Pioneer Valley branch of this national organization; and Vigils pertains to the peace and social justice vigils that Holt initiated in 1967, and continued organizing and attending until just prior to her death in 2004, and contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, leaflets, and fliers. There is visual documentation of the vigils in SERIES VII: PHOTOGRAPHS.
- SERIES V. ARTWORK 1920-2004, 9 linear ft.
  This series contains six subseries, Writings, Conservation, Drawings and paintings, Sketchbooks, Copy photographs and slides, and Artwork by others. The first two subseries describe Holt's work as an artist, and efforts by Lee and Margaret Holt to have some of the better paintings cleaned, repaired, and conserved. The drawings and paintings themselves are arranged by subject, with larger items filed in oversize boxes. The sketchbooks are filed chronologically, and many of them contain musings, political commentary, and brief diary entries in addition to drawings.
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS 1899-2003, 7 linear ft.
  This series contains photographs and transparencies of four generations of the Goddard and Holt families and their friends, including formal portraits and snapshots, travel photographs, and visual documentation of vigils and other political actions. With the exception of photographs of Margaret Holt's and Lee Holt's respective childhoods and images of earlier generations, virtually all of the photographs were taken by Lee E. Holt after he and Margaret married in 1939.
- SERIES VII. SUBJECT FILES 1912-2004, 10.25 linear ft.
  This series contains materials pertaining to Margaret Goddard Holt's lifelong interest in the many facets of peace and social justice activism at the local, state, national, and international levels. The bulk of the series is comprised of four subseries, Countries, Death penalty, Peace and disarmament, and Politics, reflecting the issues of most concern to Holt. All subseries are arranged alphabetically either by topic or by organization name.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Family history
    - Goddard, [see also Memorabilia]
      - Genealogies by Florence Louise Goddard and family treeundated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - Valentine card, clipping, and poem by Lucius P. Goddard 1850, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "A Manuscript on Slavery by Joseph Bachellor Goddard, 1794-1842," edited by Eleanor G. Worthen: typescript 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Inventory of Cummington, Massachusetts house contents 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Holt: genealogy, wills, and family newsletters 1946-49, undated, [see also Oversize Box 107] (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Holt, Margaret Goddard
    - Autobiographical statements, eulogies, obituaries, and condolence letters 1973-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Birth and marriage certificates, passports, driver's license, developmental profile chart, and Social Security card 1963-81, [see also Oversize Box 107] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes exchanged with Jeanine Maland re: Holt wishing to end her lifecirca 2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Articles and clippings 1918-2003, [see also SERIES IV. ACTIVISM, and Oversize Box 107] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sophia Smith Collection: copies of Certificate of Gift and related correspondence 1984-86 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 80th birthdayOctober 31, 1991, [see also SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS, and Oversize Box 113]
      - Clipping, poems, and speech by Margaret Holt (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Birthday cards and letters (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Awards and honors
      - 1962-2004, undated, [see also Oversize Box 107] (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
      - "AFSC Honors Margaret Holt": guest book 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Address books 1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Calendars
      - 1960, 1973-74 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
      - 1977-84 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
      - 1985-99 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
      - 2000-03 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
    - Financial information: donations to organizations
      - Lists 1983, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Acknowledgements, receipts, and related correspondence
        - Civic and environmental 1996-2003 (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - Death penalty repeal and prisoners' rights 1990-2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Humanitarian aid, civil and reproductive rights, and economic and social justice 1968-2003 (Box 6, Folder 2-5)
        - Middle East peace 1973-2003, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
        - Peace and disarmament (global) 1979-2003, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
        - Native American rights 1999-2002, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People 1977-2002, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Books and quotes that held meaning for Margaret Holt 1876-88, undated (Box 7, Folder 5-8)
  - Other family members
    - Goddard, Fanny Reed
      - Marriage announcement, death certificate, obituary, and related documents 1950-51, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Diaries 1930-49 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Goddard, Harold Clarke
      - Passport, obituaries, and clippings 1923-75 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Employment and retirement: articles, clippings, and correspondence 1946, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Goddard, Florence Louise
      - Autobiographical writings and financial information 1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Observations about family members 1918, 1941, undated (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - Holt, Alison: childhood artwork and writings 1950-54, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Holt, Daisy
      - Theater program 1923 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Diary entry (?)21 Aug 1933 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Holt, Geoffrey Lincoln: school records and related correspondence, and childhood drawings and writings 1941-54, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Holt, Lee Elbert
      - Birth certificate, name change documents, passports, psychological profile, clippings, and legal and financial information 1912-46, [see also Oversize Box 107] (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Academic records 1929-40 (Box 8, Folder 13)
        - Study abroad in Switzerland and Germany: correspondence from parents and friends, and receipts 1928-29 (Box 8, Folder 14)
        - Rhodes Scholar application 1932 (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Articles and clippings 1977-80, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - "Leo Malley interviews Lee E. Holt": videocassetteJul 2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Reed, Lewis: obituary and estate settlement 1950-54 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Walker, Florence Hammersly: eulogy, and correspondence about her death 1954, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Worthen, Ben: Bar Mitzvah program 1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Worthen, Eleanor Goddard and Eugene Mark Goddard: eulogies, legal documents, and artwork 1990-99, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Worthen, Helena Harlow (Holly): biographical information and clippings 1986-90 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia
    - "Medical Chest of a Poetical Practitioner, H. M. Thorne" undated (Box 10)
    - Bible history 1814-15 (2 miniature books) (Box 10)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Holt, Margaret
    - Goddard family (parents and other relatives)
      - 1920-39 (Box 11, Folder 1-13)
      - 1940-43 (Box 12, Folder 1-12)
      - 1944-74, 1999, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-13)
    - Holt, Lee, [see also Lee E. Holt correspondence]
      - Oct 1934 - Jun 1937 (Box 14, Folder 1-22)
      - Jul 1937 - Aug 1939 (Box 15, Folder 1-13)
      - Apr 1941-1982, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-6)
    - Worthen, Eleanor Goddard, [see also Eleanor Goddard Worthen correspondence]
      - 1928-61 (Box 16, Folder 7-13)
      - 1962-82, undated (Box 17, Folder 1-8)
    - Employment 1936 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Friends and acquaintances
      - Ahrens, Lois 1989-99 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Ajrami, Abed: incoming 1995-96, undated, [see also Gloria Emerson correspondence] (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Anastasi, Brian 1993 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Baron, Edith (Box 17)
        - Outgoing
          - 1971-84 (Box 17, Folder 13-16)
          - 1985-92, undated (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
        - Incoming 1976-87 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Bryan, Ashley 2002 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - Childs, Edith and Emma 1977-81, undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Coldham, Leah 1999-2002 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - Conroy, Emma 1955-82, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Crowe, Frances 2001-02 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - Eissler, K.R. 1968-75, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - Elkisch, Paula
        - Outgoing
          - 1941-81 (Box 18, Folder 14-19)
          - undated (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
          - Travel
            - Europe 1974-75 (Box 19, Folder 3)
            - Western U.S. 1970-73 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Incoming
          - 1951-78, undated (Box 19, Folder 5-9)
          - Enclosures and third party correspondence 1968-75, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Emerson, Gloria 1995-97, [see also Abed Ajrami correspondence] (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Evans, Nancy 1971-2003, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Foster, Barbara
        - Outgoing 1989 (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Incoming 1986-90, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Frazier, Marian 2002-03, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Hennessey, Ann 1994-2001, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Hoglund, Irene 1933-91, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Holzberger, Elizabeth Gary
        - Outgoing
          - 1984-2001 (Box 20, Folder 7-11)
          - 2002 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
          - 2003 (Box 21, Folder 3)
          - Fragmentsundated (Box 21, Folder 4-5)
        - Incoming 1979-2003, undated (Box 21, Folder 6-11)
        - Third party 1979-84, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Johnston, Randolph 1974-82 (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - Lafore, Gertrude
        - Outgoing 1969, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 14)
        - Incoming (Box 21)
          - 1975-81 (Box 21, Folder 15-18)
          - 1982-90, undated (Box 22, Folder 1-10)
      - Lee, Matthew
        - Correspondence 1987-92, n.d (Box 22, Folder 11)
        - Writings, publications, and information about Inner City Press 1988-92, undated (Box 22, Folder 12)
        - Publications: Inner City Press 1989-92, [see also Oversize Box 107] (Box 22)
      - Livengood, Eleanor 1991-2000, undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - Lowell, Jeannine 1993-2003, undated (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Luce, Donald 1978-2002, undated (includes related documents) (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Margolin, Marianne 1992-2003 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - McManus, Maggie 1991-99 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Miller, Lyle and Roy 1998-2003 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Miranda, Christopher 1997-2002, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Morgan, Carol 1982 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Murphy, Mary
        - Outgoing 1988-2003 (Box 23, Folder 7)
        - Incoming 2002-03 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Pappenheim, Yvonne 1981-2003, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Praetz, Kitty and Rudy
        - Outgoing
          - 1964-90, undated (Box 23, Folder 10-11)
          - Travel
            - Europe 1974-75 (Box 23, Folder 12)
            - Western U.S., 1970-73 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - Incoming 1974-90 (Box 24, Folder 2)
        - Third party 1979 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Riess, Anneliese 1976-2002 (Box 24, Folder 4-5)
      - Robischon, Mary (Marget) 1988-2003 (Box 24, Folder 6-9)
      - Schatzkamer, Mary Bray 1987, undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
      - Schroeder, Paul and Mazie 1998-2003 (Box 24, Folder 11)
      - Serota, Arthur 1981-86 (Box 24, Folder 12)